Abraham: When designers create a
new system, they often start by
looking at what the system needs
to do and what it should look like.
But when designing any system, it
is always important to consider
cyber security as an integral part
of the design process in order to
create a system that is robust.
Nicole: Traditionally organisations
have been more reactive to cyber
security, but this can be a costly
process in more ways than one.
By being proactive and designing systems
with cyber security already built in they
are limiting the opportunity for tech
savvy hackers to create maximum damage.
Abraham: If the specifications of
a system highlight cyber security
as integral, then the system will
be designed around that criterion.
Nicole: Before a system is designed it
should be looked at carefully to see
what data, connections, people, and
other systems may be needed for it to
operate and how these need to be taken
into consideration regarding security.
The point at which any cyber attack could
happen should be thoroughly reviewed.
This should be at every point at which
data is stored, manipulated, or rendered.
Abraham: It is also important to
assess what risks cannot be accepted
and what the consequences of an
attack would be at every level.
Companies should always do a risk
analysis beforehand to assess where the
potential problems might lie and what the
consequences might be if cyber security
is not implemented from the beginning.
Nicole: Everyone involved in the
design process should also consider
the cost of not doing something
versus the cost of doing it.
So, what would happen when a system
stops functioning due to a cyber-attack.
It can greatly impact both users
of the system and the organisation
who owns and manages the system.
Abraham: Unauthorised access may
mean that the system has been
modified or had its data destroyed,
meaning that if a ‘backup’ is not
available all that data may be lost.
Also, all that data accessed, could
be sold on, or given to others to use.
Nicole: You only have to look at the
impact this has had on companies and
organisations such as Eurofins scientific
who were infected by ransomware
and the NHS which was brought to a
standstill by the WannaCry outbreak.
For more information on
this check out our weblinks.
Abraham: Costs don’t just involve
repairing or patching a system
or payment of ‘ransoms’ to get a
system back online or retrieve data.
They involved much greater costs
such as being fined under GDPR or NIS
legislation as well as general business
costs, and major reputational damage
let alone the chance of litigation.
There are also issues related to
loss of trust amongst customers,
users or suppliers and an inability
to meet contractual obligations.
Nicole: So, if the worst happens
and a system is found vulnerable,
what are the consequences?
If data is imported from an external
or less trusted source it may have
been designed to attack a system.
Employees at all levels should be made
aware of the consequences of a data
breach and their own responsibility
as part of the organisation.
Abraham: It is always important that
structure data can be validated or
else it should be transformed, or
it needs to be rendered carefully.
The complexity of malicious code
in documents means that it is
safer to transform the file or
content into another format.
Nicole: Checking that the structure
and content of data is as expected goes
some way to ensuring that malicious code
will not be injected into a system, but
this only works in simple file formats.
If validation and transformation are
not possible rendering information in
a disposable environment not linked
to the system is the best option.
Abraham: However, as we said earlier,
by adding security at the beginning
in the design stage all these issues
can be factored into the process to
make a system as secure as possible.